Finding aid to the War Service collection CA.MS.00352
Smith College Archives
War Service collection
1905-1992
Smith College Archives
War Service
CA.MS.00352
4 boxes (1.7 linear feet)
Contains correspondence, reports, news articles, publications, and photographs, related to War Service in World War I.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in the Smith College Archives are open for use, with the following exceptions: "Office Files," files of records created for the use of the administrative unit that created them, are closed to research for a period of 10 years following their creation. In all cases, the College Archives will continue to provide public access to materials that were intended to be public at the time of their creation (press releases, publications, etc.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records of the War Service Records were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into seven series:
Series I: Near East Unit
Series II: Red Cross Relief Unit
Series III: Smith College Refugee Unit
Series IV: Serbian Relief Unit
Series V: Other College Programs
Series VI: Smith College Canteen Unit
Series VII: War Service Board
Biographical / Historical
The War Service Records focus on a small group of relief workers and their respective projects. Many of these volunteers were part of larger Smith units that were overseen by the American Red Cross, which was actively working overseas during, and immediately after, World War I. Most of these Smith groups were small, consisting of only 5-10 members. Their recollections are primarily in the form of extensive correspondence, both to family and the War Service Board. The collection documents not only post-war conditions in Europe and the Middle East, but also the social life of the volunteers. Due to strict censors, many of these letters were edited by the authors, in turn leaving out key information and specific details of their locations and work. In addition to parsing the letters down, many letters home were lost or failed to pass the censors, leaving the correspondence nonlinear and disorganized.
There is little background on the group of Smith relief workers sent to the Near East. Working under the supervision of the 'American Committee for Relief in the Near East,' a Red Cross organization, the volunteers worked in what is now known as the Middle East-specifically Turkey, Syria, Armenia, and Kurdistan. These volunteers were deployed during WWI to repair the damage wrought to these areas by conflict and battle. Many of these women were trained as nurses or experienced in social work; their primary responsibility was to make the local populations self-sufficient.
The Red Cross Relief Unit series contains materials relating to both Smith College and the Red Cross, as well as their combined efforts to create Smith relief units. The material in the collection does not relate to specific relief groups, but rather to the larger organizations. The series also contains commemorative material relating to Smith graduates who worked for the Red Cross, but were not members of one of the major relief units.
The Smith College Refugee Unit was formed at the request of the Smith College Relief Unit (SCRU) director, Hannah Dunlop Andrews. SCRU consisted of five social workers sent to work under the Refugee Bureau of the Red Cross in Orleans, France. Its director was Anne Chapin, Class of 1904, a SCRU member. The series is comprised mainly of volunteer correspondence. The letters express both the satisfaction the volunteers found in their work and the conditions of war-torn France, as well as the dismay they felt when the Red Cross decided to close its refugee camps.
The Serbian Relief Unit was sent to an orphanage near Belgrade, with a specific request for nurses and kindergarten teachers. Supervising the Serbian Relief Unit was the Child Welfare Association, whose purpose was to send aid to those areas not already receiving relief. It was under this unit that Elizabeth Williams, Class of 1891, began an orphanage in Serbia. Included in the collection are descriptive letters by kindergarten teacher Charlotte Wiggin, Class of 1908, and extensive correspondence by Williams herself. The letters relay the hopes of the volunteers, as well as the day-to-day tasks of running the unit.
'Other College Programs' is a small series that includes material from both the Vassar Training Camp for Nurses and the Wellesley Good Will Delegation. Smith graduates participated in both of these programs, though these alumnae were not affiliated with the respective colleges. These programs offered pertinent advice and skills to upcoming volunteers.
In 1918, the head of the Women's Overseas Council of the Y.M.C.A. approached New York Smith alumnae, suggesting that they form a unit of 10 women to serve as canteen workers in France. In June, the Alumnae Association endorsed the Smith College Canteen as a necessary war service activity, and the New York alumnae undertook the task of fundraising for the unit. After receiving permission from President William A. Neilson to form the unit, 10 Smith alumnae set sail in late spring, under the supervision of the Y.M.C.A. Harriet Ford Bliss, Class of 1899 and a SCRU relief worker, was asked to represent the SCCU in Paris. Second and third Canteen Units followed this first group. Upon arrival of the third group in France, the war was commencing and the Smith volunteers were only allowed to stay for the summer months. The purpose of the canteen unit was to offer supplies and serve meals to those who did not have access to the Y.M.C.A. relief huts stationed around France. These women volunteers rode in a Ford truck around the countryside, serving up to 2,000 meals daily, socializing with the locals, and providing soldiers with cigarettes and playing cards.
Scope and Contents
This collection focuses on the World War I relief efforts of Smith College students and graduates who were not part of the Smith College Relief Unit (SCRU). The collection is comprised primarily of volunteer files, which include correspondence, scrapbooks, photographs, and some memorabilia. Also included are official records consisting of organizational material and financial/personnel records. The collection also includes papers related to war on Smith campus and the activities of the War Service Board.
War Service
- SERIES I. NEAR EAST RELIEF UNIT
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family, Feb-June 1919 (Box 160, Folder 1)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family, July-Sept 1919 (Box 160, Folder 2)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family, Oct-Dec 1919 (Box 160, Folder 3)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family, 1920 (Box 160, Folder 4)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to family, Jan-May 1920 (Box 160, Folder 5)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence from father, June 1919-May 1920 (Box 160, Folder 6)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence to War Service Board, 1919-1924 (Box 160, Folder 7)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Correspondence, miscellaneous, Feb 1919-July 1923 (Box 160, Folder 8)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Manuscript, 1923; undated (Box 160, Folder 9)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Near East Relief handbook, Jan 1919-Oct 1920 (Box 160, Folder 10)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Reports of relief work, 1919-1920 (Box 160, Folder 11)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Photographs, undated (Box 160, Folder 12)
  - Greene, Esther (1901): Photographs, undated (Box 160, Folder 13)
  - Guest, Elma Cokefair: Correspondence, Aug 1919-Feb 1920 (Box 160, Folder 14)
  - Henry, Ruth Whipple (1908): Correspondence (Box 160, Folder 15)
    General
    [See also Smith College Relief Unit records- Mary Goodman (1901) and Box 161- photograph album] Feb 1919-Nov 1920
  - Hill, Justine Hamilton (1916): Correspondence to War Service Board (Box 160, Folder 16)
    [See also Smith College Honorary Degree files] Feb 1919-March 1920
  - Mitchell, Myra (1906): Correspondence to War Service Board, Feb 1919- Nov 1920 (Box 160, Folder 17)
  - Moore, Alice (1912): Correspondence to War Service Board, Feb 1919- Nov 1920 (Box 160, Folder 18)
  - Henry, Ruth Whipple (1908): Photograph album, 1921 (Box 161)
- SERIES II. RED CROSS RELIEF UNIT
  - General: Pamphlets and pins, 1914-1920 (Box 162, Folder 1)
  - Individuals (Box 162)
    - Letters of Elizabeth Stearns Tyler: Publication, 1920 (Box 162, Folder 2)
    - Rice, Marion McCune (1905): Clippings, 1905-1992 (Box 162, Folder 3)
    - Young, Dorothy Amy (1902): Medical record, 1919 (Box 162, Folder 4)
- SERIES III. SMITH COLLEGE REFUGEE UNIT
  - General, undated (Box 162, Folder 5)
  - Individuals (Box 162)
    - Merrill, Ida (1906): Correspondence to Lewis, Mary, 1918 (Box 162, Folder 6)
    - Mitchell, Myra Agnes (1906): Correspondence, 1919 (Box 162, Folder 7)
    - Shaffer, Lucy Kennedy (1908): Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 162, Folder 8)
- SERIES IV. SERBIAN RELIEF UNIT
  - General, undated (Box 162, Folder 9)
  - Individuals (Box 162)
    - Childs, Carolyn Helfenstien (1902): Letter, 1925 (Box 162, Folder 10)
    - Wiggin, Charlotte (1908): Correspondence, 1920 (Box 162, Folder 11)
    - Williams, Elizabeth Sprague (1891): Correspondence, 1919-1921 (Box 162, Folder 12)
- SERIES V. OTHER COLLEGE PROGRAMS
  - Vassar Training Camp for Nurses: Photographs, 1918 (Box 162, Folder 13)
  - Wellesley Good Will Delegation: Photographs, 1923 (Box 162, Folder 14)
- SERIES VI. SMITH COLLEGE CANTEEN UNIT
  - General and organizational materials, 1918-1919 (Box 163, Folder 1)
  - Financial material, 1918 (Box 163, Folder 2)
  - Individuals
    - Blodgett, Ruth Robinson (1905): Correspondence, 1919 (Box 163, Folder 3)
    - Clark, Anne Elizabeth (1921): Clipping and letter, 1922 (Box 163, Folder 4)
    - Jenkins, Anna Spaulding (1890): Correspondence and clipping, 1919 (Box 163, Folder 5)
    - Russell, Elizabeth Lincoln (1903): Correspondence, undated (Box 163, Folder 6)
  - Unit 1
    - Abbe, Ruth Kennard (1911): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 7)
    - Bowman, Agnes Gertrude (1911): Correspondence, 1918 (Box 163, Folder 8)
    - Durkee, Helen Winslow (1902): Correspondence, 1918 (Box 163, Folder 9)
    - Fullerton, Pauline V. (1905): Correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box 163, Folder 10)
    - Howe, Mary Reed (1902): Report, 1920 (Box 163, Folder 11)
    - McCluney, Mildred (1904): Report and photograph, 1918-1919 (Box 163, Folder 12)
    - Seeber, Elizabeth (1908): Correspondence and photographs, 1918-1920; undated (Box 163, Folder 13)
    - Seymour, Mary (ex-1899): Correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box 163, Folder 14)
    - Souther, Edith (1902): Correspondence and report, 1918-1919; undated (Box 163, Folder 15)
    - Tuthill, Stella (1907): Correspondence, 1918-1921; undated (Box 163, Folder 16)
    - Wilson, Jean Shaw (1901): Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 163, Folder 17)
    - Witherbee, Edna (Schell) (1908): Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 163, Folder 18)
  - Unit 2
    - Bean, Margaret (1913): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 19)
    - Bridgers, Ann (1915): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 20)
    - Eis, Florence Marion (1916): Postcard, 1921 (Box 163, Folder 21)
    - Hammond, May (1903): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 22)
    - James, Isabel (1912): Correspondence, 1919-1920; undated (Box 163, Folder 23)
    - Nash, Margaret (1904): Correspondence, 1919-1921 (Box 163, Folder 24)
    - Roberts, Mildred Frances (1915): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 25)
    - Scandrett, Rebekah (1915): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 26)
    - Williams, Olive (1912): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 27)
  - Unit 3
    - Beane, Katherine Edna (1908): Overview of service, 1921 (Box 163, Folder 28)
    - Frankenstein, Sally Moss (1912): Correspondence, 1920 (Box 163, Folder 29)
    - Hodgeman, Helen E. (1913): Photographs, passport, 1919; undated (Box 163, Folder 30)
    - Hugus, Elizabeth (1916): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 31)
    - Hunt, Harriet Larnard (1913): Photographs, 1919 (Box 163, Folder 32)
    - Knight, Katherine (1914): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 33)
    - Vermilye, Katherine Rowland (1915): Postcard, 1920 (Box 163, Folder 34)
    - Wingate, Gladys Isabel (1908): Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 163, Folder 35)
- SERIES I. NEAR EAST UNIT, 1919-1924
  Scope and Contents
  This series documents the work of Smith students and graduates in the Near East. The bulk of this series consists of the extensive correspondence of Esther Greene, Class of 1901, to her family in the United States. Greene's files include many photographs of the areas that she worked in, as well as photographs of volunteers and local residents. Also included is the correspondence of Greene's fellow volunteers. Much of this correspondence is with the War Service Board. Ruth Henry Whipple's, Class of 1908, photograph album is also included in this series. The Near East records provide a detailed look into the life of relief workers, particularly those who worked with children, established orphanages, and who were interested in hygiene.
- SERIES II. RED CROSS RELIEF, 1905-1992
  This series documents the work of Smith College volunteers for the Red Cross in France. There is organizational material included, as well as instructions for incoming volunteers. Most of the organizational records consist of correspondence in both English and French. The remainder of the collection includes material relating to specific volunteers. Included is a published book of letters written by Smith volunteer, Elizabeth Stearns Tyler, Class of 1909.
- SERIES III. SMITH COLLEGE REFUGEE UNIT, 1918-1919
  This series documents the work of the Smith College Refugee Unit in France. The majority of the collection consists of correspondence by three of the five volunteers. There is a small amount of background material pertaining to the unit.
- SERIES IV. SERBIAN RELIEF UNIT, 1918-1925
  This documents the work of a small group of women sent to do relief work in Serbia. Some background information is included, but the majority of the materials are information files on three of the volunteers. These files are primarily correspondence, with some organizational material.
- SERIES V. OTHER COLLEGE PROGRAMS, 1918-1923
  This series contains records of two relief programs sponsored by Wellesley College and Vassar College in which Smith graduates participated. Materials consist of photographs, primarily from loose scrapbook pages.
- SERIES VI. SMITH COLLEGE CANTEEN UNIT, 1918-1922
  The vast majority of the material in this series consists of the correspondence of SCCU volunteers, from each of the three Canteen Units. Also included in these files is some miscellaneous material. The remainder of the collection consists of memorabilia and photographs, as well as financial and organizational material.
- Series VII. War Service Board, 4 boxes
  This series contains papers related to the activities of the War Service Board and war related activities on Smith campus.